Guide to the Save the Wetlands Committee, Inc. of Connecticut Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Save the Wetlands Committee, Inc. of Connecticut records
1956-1977
MS 1434
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
(12 boxes, 1 roll)
The records consist of correspondence, minutes, reports, topical files, maps, and other materials documenting the activities of Save the Wetlands, Inc. The records include files kept by committee president Freeborn G. Jewett and treasurer Frederick Pope, Jr. and highlight the committee's educational, public relations, lobbying, and monitoring activities.
Save the Wetlands Committee
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Freeborn G. Jewett, 1985; Martin Wright, 1986; and Frederick Pope, Jr., 1986.
Scope and Contents
The Save the Wetlands Committee, Inc. of Connecticut Records consist of correspondence, minutes, reports, topical files, maps, and other materials which document the committee's activities to assist in the preservation of tidal marshes in the state. The records include files kept by committee president Freeborn G. Jewett and treasurer Frederick Pope, Jr. which highlight the committee's educational, public relations, lobbying, and monitoring activities.
The records, which were donated to the Yale Library by Freeborn Jewett in 1985 and by Martin Wright and Frederick Pope, Jr. in 1986, are arranged in thirteen boxes. The records are arranged by donor and reflect the donors' arrangement of their papers. Boxes 1-8 and Common Folio, folder 87 include records received from Freeborn Jewett; box 9 was donated by Martin Wright and contains a scrapbook of clippings documenting the activities of the committee; and boxes 10-12 are composed of records donated by Frederick Pope, Jr. Both the Jewett and Pope files are arranged by topic and contain similar or duplicate material. The Jewett files contain a wider range of subjects, while the Pope files are more focused on financial and legislative matters. The correspondence in the Pope files (folders 75-84) also helps document the activities of the committee prior to 1966 Aug and to Freeborn Jewett's involvement with the work of the committee.
The records include organizational papers of the committee such as minutes, incorporation documents, by-laws, and membership lists (folders 40, 71-74, and 93-95). There is correspondence in nearly all the files, but chronological files of general correspondence in folders 17 to 23 and 75 to 84 detail the overall history and development of the committee's policies and programs. Major correspondents include Richard H. Pough of the National Areas Council and consultant Walter S. Boardman. Copies of the committee's publications and press releases also detail the progress of the committee in organizing its educational campaign and in garnering public support. Committee newsletters are in folders 3-4; press releases are in folders 43-51 and 94-95; copies of the Brenneman report are in folders 59 and 93; and other publications are in folder 53. Files concerning the 1968 Save the Wetlands Conference are in folders 5-16. Transcripts of the conference and copies of the papers delivered at the conference are in folders 10-12 and folder 99. Drafts of proposed legislation along with the transcripts of committee members' testimony at hearings are in folders 28-35, 52, and 91-92. The files also contain a large quantity of background reference material in the form of maps; newsletters and bulletins from other organizations; copies of wetlands protective legislation adopted by other states; printed articles and reports; and clippings. Included in folders 41 and 42 are color aerial photographs of Connecticut's coastal marshes.
Biographical / Historical
The Save the Wetlands Committee was formed in 1966, at the instigation of Allan F. Kitchel, Jr., and was incorporated in 1967. Its stated purpose was to establish a program for the preservation and protection of Connecticut's coastal and inland wetlands. Through its educational program of publications and meetings it worked to garner public support for legislation protecting Connecticut's marshes from dredging, land fill, and commercial development.
The Committee was advised and supported by the National Areas Council and the National Audobon Society and received major grants from the Avalon Foundation, the Old Dominion Foundation, and the American Conservation Association to finance its program. The citizens' committee was led by Freeborn Jewett as its president and Frederick Pope, Jr. as its treasurer and employed Walter S. Boardman as a consultant; Peter H. Borgemeister as executive secretary; and Martin Wright and Associates to perform public relations work. The Committee had its office at 103 Bingham Laboratory on the Yale campus.
From 1967 to 1969 the committee was engaged in intense activity to educate the public to the need for wetlands protection and to prepare the way for passage of a Connecticut "Save the Wetlands" act. The committee sponsored a large Save the Wetlands Conference at Yale in December 1968 and circulated copies of a report to the committee by Russell L. Brenneman on public regulation of coastal wetlands in Connecticut. Committee members worked with state officials, such as Senator Joseph B. Buckley, Senator J. W. Jackson, Senator George Gunther, Representative Mary B. Griswold, and Department of Agriculture and Natural Resources Commissioner Joseph Gil, to draft adequate legislation.
The "Save the Wetlands" act became effective on October 1, 1969, as Public Act 695. Following the successful campaign for its passage the committee turned its attention to monitoring the act's implementation and followed various law suits stemming from changes brought by the new law. By 1976 committee members felt that their goals had been achieved and that the law was being suitably enforced. They, therefore, voted to dissolve the Save the Wetlands Committee, Inc. of Connecticut.
Conservation of natural resources -- Law and legislation -- Connecticut; Environmental protection; Marshes -- Connecticut; Salt marshes -- Connecticut; Wetland conservation -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Maps; Photoprints; Boardman, Walter S.; Borgemeister, Peter H.; Brenneman, Russell L., 1928-2016; Jewett, F. G. (Freeborn G.); Pope, Frederick; Pough, Richard H. (Richard Hooper), 1904-2003; Connecticut Audubon Society; Martin Wright and Associates, Inc. (Guilford, Conn.); National Areas Council; National Audubon Society; Save the Wetlands Committee
- Inventory
  - Acquisitions, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boardman, Walter S., 1967-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins and newsletters, 1968-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Connecticut Wetlands Conference
    - Participants, 1968-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Preparations, 1964-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Printed material, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - Public relations, 1967-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1967-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-23)
  - Films, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Laws, 1963-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
  - Legislation, 1967-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 28-35)
  - Marshes
    - Essex, 1965-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Guilford, Old Lyme, others, 1967-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - National Audubon Society and Connecticut Audubon Council, 1967-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - Organizational papers, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
  - Press releases, 1967-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 43-51)
  - Protests and hearings, 1967-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Publications, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Reference material, 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 54-61)
  - Reference material, 1970-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 62-66)
  - Town representatives, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 67-68)
  - "A Vanishing Resource…", 1967-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Foundation, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Incorporation, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Minutes, 1967-1977 (Box 7, Folder 72-4)
  - Maps, undated (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook: clippings, 1967-1972 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 9)
  - Oversize (Box 13)
- Additional Material, Accession 1987-M-017
  - Correspondence, 1965-1970 (Box 10, Folder 75-84)
  - Financial records, 1967-1969, undated (Box 11, Folder 85-89)
  - Goodwin, George, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 90)
  - Legislation: House and Senate, 1956-1969 (Box 11, Folder 91-92)
  - Minutes and press releases, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 93-95)
  - Printed material, 1960-1969 (Box 12, Folder 96-98)
  - Reports, 1962, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 99-100)
  - Water resources problems, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - Miscellanea, 1967-1970, undated (Box 12, Folder 102-103)